Register of the O. (Ol'ga) Morozova papers
Hoover Institution Archives
O. Morozova papers,
1888-1968
2001C11
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, and photographs, relating to Russian literature, Russian émigré affairs, and post-World War II Russian refugees in the Philippines.
Morozova, O. (Ol'ga), 1877-1968
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Ol'ga Morozova was born Ol'ga Kolesova in Khar'kov on 3 July 1877 (N. S.), the daughter of the principal of the Khar'kov Agricultural School. Graduating from the Khar'kov women's institute in 1895, she established, with her own funds, a primary school for peasant children on the outskirts of Khar'kov. In the same year, she began a career as a journalist in various local papers and journals, also authoring a number of popular books on agricultural issues. She married the livestock specialist Iona M. Morozov and moved with him to Semipalatinsk in 1911, turning her energies to relief and nursing work with the Russian Red Cross during the First World War. In 1918 she established a 50-bed hospital in Semipalatinsk.
The Bolshevik advance in 1919 forced her to leave Semipalatinsk with her son Boris (her husband and a daughter, evacuating Omsk with Admiral Kolchak, were killed; another daughter, Vera, escaped by other means). Living in various towns and cities in China in the early 1920s, she finally moved to Tientsin in 1928, enduring a lengthy trek through the Gobi desert. It was in Tientsin that Morozova wrote most of the novels that gained her a literary reputation, such as Sud'ba, Nevozvratnoe, and Nora. Like many of her compatriots who evacuated China in the late forties and early fifties, Ol'ga Morozova spent some time in the Tubabao refugee camp before being admitted to the United States in 1951, an experience she chronicled in unpublished memoirs. Morozova died in Los Angeles on 1 January 1968.
Chronology
1877 July 3 Born, Khar'kov, Russia
1895 Established an elementary school near Khar'kov
1901 April 27 Married Iona Morozov
1911 Moved to Semipalatinsk, Russia
1915 Appointed assistant director for army meat supply for Western Siberia
1920 Iona Morozov killed in Civil War
1932 Author, Nevozvratnoe
1934 Author, Sud'ba
1949 Evacuated to Tubabao refugee camp, Philippines
1951 Arrived in the United States
1958 Author, Kak pomoch' bol'nomu cheloveku
1968 January 1 Died, Los Angeles, California
1984 Sud'ba reprinted
Scope and Content Note
Olga Morozova was a novelist who published several works in China in the 1930s. This collection contains her rare and unpublished writings, including reminiscences of Tubabao, a camp in the Philippines for Russian displaced persons from the Far East, and collected materials for a biographical dictionary of prominent Russian émigrés, entitled "Kul'turnye sily rossiiskoi emigratsii."
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
China.; Philippines.; Refugees.; Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians--China.; Russians--Philippines.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1888-1968
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiographical note, clippings, curriculum vitae, identity papers, immigration records, and television program transcripts, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Autobiographical note (Reel 1)
    Box/Folder 1: 1
  - Birth certificate
    Box/Folder 1: 2
  - Clippings about or mentioning Ol'ga Morozova
    Box/Folder 1: 3. Includes obituaries.
  - Curriculum vitae
    Box/Folder 1: 4
  - Immigration papers
    Box/Folder 1: 5
  - Television program transcripts
    Box/Folder 1: 6. Includes Russian translations, additional associated correspondence, and letters of thanks by Morozova's daughter to George Putnam for his televised report on Ol'ga Morozova.
  - Miscellany
    Box/Folder 1: 7
- Correspondence, 1939-1952
  - Beliaev, Efim Pavlovich, 1939-1940
    Box/Folder 1: 8
  - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1948-1952
    Box/Folder 1: 9
- Speeches and Writings, 1953-1965, undated
  Article and books arranged chronologically by title.
  - "Kul'turnye sily russkoi emigratsii,", undated
    - Background materials
      Box/Folder 1: 10-15. Primarily newspaper clippings (obituaries) with attached photographs, and other compiled information.
    - Background materials (Reel 2)
      Box/Folder 1: 16 and 2: 1-2.
    - Holograph
      Box/Folder 2: 3-6
  - "Tubabao: Lager' IRO russkikh belykh emigrantov," typescript, 1953 (Reel 3)
    Box/Folder 3: 1
  - Kak pomoch' bol'nomu cheloveku, 2nd edition, revised and enlarged, 1958
    Box/Folder 3: 2
  - "World Law Day," Los Angeles Herald-Examiner, 1965 September 13
    Box/Folder 3: 3. Printed copy and congratulatory letter from Charles Warren, California State Assemblyman.
- Photographs, 1949-1950
  Box/Folder 3: 4. Album of photographs of the Tubabao camp.